Arnheid.
阿奴纳
Then this must be Ketil's farm.
那么这里一定是凯特尔的农场
Who would have thought...
谁能想到...
You guys were so close.
你们就在附近
It was a walking distance of few days.
走路几天就到了
You look a bit drawn.
你看起来有点憔悴
But you are even more
但你现在变得...
beautiful than before.
比以前更漂亮了
What? That is Arnheid's husband?
什么?那是阿奴纳的丈夫?
Is Hjalti doing well?
贾赫提还好吗?
I bet he's grown a lot by now.
他现在一定长大许多了吧
Gardar...
哥达
Hjalti is...
贾赫提他...
Come on.
来吧
Let's go back. The three of us.
我们三人一起回去吧
To our home.
回我们的家
Home?
家?
Don't take his hand, Arnheid!
别牵他的手 阿奴纳
If you do, I'll cut you down.
如果你这么做的话 我会宰了你
- Gardar! - Fox!
-哥达 -狐
- Take Arnheid and stay behind me. - Yes!
-把阿奴纳带到我身后 -好
Something's off about him, Boss.
他有点不太对劲 老大
For a second it seemed like he forgot that he was on the run.
有一瞬间他似乎忘了他在逃亡
Is it true that Lizard was killed?
蜥蜴真的被杀死了吗?
Yes. His head was smashed.
对 他的头都被打烂了
I see.
了解
He's here to take Arnheid away.
他打算把拿阿奴纳带走
Guard her with your life.
用你的性命保护她
Yes!
好
Are you Ketil?
你是凯特尔吗?
What if I am?
如果我是呢?
I'll kill you!
那我就会杀了你
Stop it, Gardar! This is insane!
住手 哥达 这太荒唐了
Gardar!
哥达
Stop, Einar!
别过去 埃纳尔
You don't know the whole story. What are you thinking?
你不了解事情的全貌 你这是在干嘛?
Are you going to attack Snake?
你想攻击蛇吗?
I know the story!
我知道是怎么回事
Arnheid's husband has come to save her.
阿奴纳的先生来这里救她
Don't you want Arnheid to be free?
你不希望阿奴纳重获自由吗?
I do! But look at the situation.
当然希望 但照目前的状况看来
He has to take down three people to get away.
他得击退三个人才能脱身
I know that I'm not strong enough to do anything. But still!
我知道我是在不自量力 但我还是得...
Einar! That's not what I'm trying to say.
埃纳尔 我想说的不是这个
Are you capable of killing someone?
杀人这件事 你做得到吗?
It doesn't matter if it's a guest or not.
不管他是不是客人
Can you really kill someone with this axe?
你真的能用这把斧头杀了他吗?
But...
但是...
Then what am I supposed to do?
那我还能做什么?
That's a wise choice, Thorfinn.
你做出了一个明智的选择 托尔芬
Stay there and watch quietly.
站在那里安静地看就好
I'll catch him alive.
我会活捉他
We have to question him and confirm his identity.
我们必须审问他以确认他的身份
Watch out, Boss! He's strong!
老大 小心 他很厉害
Who do you think...
你以为...
you're talking to? You idiot!
你在跟谁讲话?你这个白痴
He's not someone you can capture alive. Just kill him!
他不是你能活捉的人 把他杀了吧
Shut up!
闭嘴
That was just a light warmup.
那只是稍微热身一下而已
More like, were you guys able to strike him at least once?
我说 你们至少击中过他一次吧?
Huh? Oh, unfortunately...
什么?呃...有点丢人但...
He's injured.
他受伤了
How could the three of you lose to one wounded man.
你们三个人 怎么还打不过一个受伤的人?
Just as I thought. That's the spot.
跟我想的一样 弱点在那里
Badger, tie him up.
獾 把他绑起来
- Gardar! - Amazing! He got him in no time!
-哥达 -太神了 他立刻就扳倒他了
Gardar!
哥达
Arnheid!
阿奴纳
- Arnheid! - Walk!
-阿奴纳 -快走
Don't let your guard down.
别掉以轻心了
Always have five people watching him.
始终保持五个人监视他
Also, go and tell Kjallakr's uncle
还有 去通知凯尔拉克的叔叔
that we caught a suspect.
我们抓到了一名嫌犯
Roger.
收到
Well then...
好了...
You look like you have something to say.
你们看起来似乎有话想说
But a slave has no say in the matter.
但这种事 奴隶没有说话的余地
Can't you let him go?
你就不能放了他吗?
This is too cruel.
这太残忍了
He killed one of my men.
他杀了我一名手下
He's suspected of having killed others too.
他也涉嫌杀害其他人
On top of that, he wants to kill the master
除此之外 他想杀了主人
and steal Arnheid, who is the master's favorite.
偷走主人最爱的阿奴纳
There's no way I can let someone like that go.
我绝不可能放过这样的人
Forget about him, Arnheid.
忘了他吧 阿奴纳
That wasn't your husband.
他不是你丈夫了
It was just a crazy runaway slave.
他只是一名逃亡中的疯狂奴隶
Listen, don't get involved in this matter.
听着 别干涉这件事
Take care of Gramps for me.
帮我好好照顾老头子
- Wait, Einar. - Einar...
-等等 埃纳尔 -埃纳尔
Please stay seated.
请坐下吧
Dinner is almost ready.
晚餐就快煮好了
If it's at night...
如果是在晚上
While it's still dark, we might be able to
趁着月黑风高 我们或许能够
sneak inside the fort and rescue Gardar.
潜入堡垒 救出哥达
If we don't do anything,
如果我们不采取任何行动
your husband will be executed for sure.
你丈夫一定会被处死
I appreciate it.
我很感激
But it's fine.
但没关系
Some things are out of our control.
有些事情我们是控制不了的
When things like that happen, it's best to do nothing.
一旦遇上了这种事 最好是静观其变
You stay still
一动也不动地
and wait for the storm to pass.
等待着风暴过去
Einar, don't let yourself be caught up in the storm.
埃纳尔 别把自己卷入风暴里
Do you not
你不喜欢...
like Gardar?
哥达吗?
I do.
我喜欢
Our marriage was arranged by our parents,
我们的婚姻是双方父母作主的
but he was kind
但他很照顾我
to me and our son.
和我们的儿子
Well then, let's go!
那么 我们走吧
Even if it means fighting with Snake,
就算得与蛇正面交锋
it's better than doing nothing.
总比什么都不做的好
Isn't that right, Thorfinn?
我说的没错吧 托尔芬?
Please, Thorfinn. Lend us your help.
拜托了 托尔芬 帮帮我们吧
I'll distract the guards so you--
我会分散守卫的注意力 而你...
I...
我...
lost my son over a pot.
因为一个锅而失去了我的儿子
Will you let me talk a little about myself?
可以让我说说我的故事吗?
About my past...
关于我的过去...
Our family
我们全家
lived in a certain village in Sweden.
住在瑞典的一个村庄里
We were neither wealthy nor poor,
我们不算富有也不算贫穷
but it was peaceful.
生活很平静
Around the time our son was one,
大概在我们儿子一岁的时候
a swamp that produced iron was discovered deep within a faraway forest.
有人在遥远的森林里发现了 一个出产铁的沼泽
It led to a conflict between
为此几个团体之间起了冲突
several groups who wanted
互相争夺
rights to the swamp.
沼泽的产权
Among those involved in the conflict
那群起冲突的人当中
was Gardar's friend,
有个人是哥达的朋友
and he came to ask for his help.
他来寻求哥达的协助
Gardar told everyone in the village about it
哥达把这件事告诉了村里所有的人
and the men discussed the topic
男人开始讨论这个话题
of whether to join the fight or not.
讨论该不该加入斗争
If we win, we get iron.
如果赢了 我们就能得到铁矿
The conclusion the men came up with was
男人做出的结论是
to join.
加入
When the women heard about it, we were shocked.
村里的女人听说了之后都非常震惊
After all, our village was not
毕竟我们村并不需要
in need of pots or blades for our sickles.
制作锅、镰刀刀片的铁
Despite that,
尽管如此
there was no way for women
女人是无法
to overturn a decision made by men.
推翻男人做出的决定的
Please reconsider, Gardar.
哥达 请你考虑清楚
It's not like we're struggling because we don't have iron.
又不是没有铁 就会让我们的生活陷入困难
Why are you risking your life for something we don't even need?
你为什么要为了我们根本 不需要的东西冒上生命危险?
Arnheid...
阿奴纳
We do need it.
我们确实是需要铁的
Yngve of the west is a very ambitious man.
西边的英格是个很有野心的人
If his family gets a hold of the iron,
如果他的家族得到了铁矿
the balance of power in this area will fall apart.
这个区域的权力分配就会失衡
Plus, our village will become prosperous.
况且 我们的村子会因此变得繁荣
That includes both of you too.
我们两个也能从中获益
Hjalti!
贾赫提
Your father is going to fight to protect you.
你的爸爸为了保护你 准备要去作战了
I couldn't understand.
我无法理解
Hey! Ouch!
喂 很痛的
If he wanted to protect us,
如果他想要保护我们
all he needed to do was stay by our side.
他只需要待在我们身边就好
All of the young men went to war
所有的年轻男子都上战场了
and the women and children left behind protected the homes.
女人和孩子被留下来守护我们的家
A few weeks went by like that.
这个状况持续了几周
Then...
然后
Look...
你们看
When we saw the boats,
当船出现的时候
we thought the men had returned.
我们以为是男人回家了
But they were...
但他们...
They targeted us knowing that all the men were gone.
他们知道村里的男人都离开了 所以锁定了我们
They burned our houses and killed the elderly.
他们烧毁了我们的房子 杀死了老人家
The women were put inside boats
女人被绑上船
and taken away.
带走了
I...
我...
Hjalti was...
贾赫提...
Hjalti!
贾赫提
Stop! No! Hjalti!
住手 不要啊 贾赫提
Today, when I saw Gardar,
今天 当我见到哥达的时候
I felt terrified of him.
我感到很害怕
All of the pain he has suffered
他经历的那些痛苦
must have changed him.
想必让他变了一个人
Now, he himself
现在 他本身
is the storm.
就是风暴
This time...
这一次...
This time
这一次
I will make sure to protect
我会确保我的孩子
my child from the storm created by men.
不会被男人掀起的风暴波及
Child?
孩子?
I found out just the other day.
我前几天才知道的
Right now, I am carrying Master Ketil's child.
我现在怀着主人凯特尔的孩子
I'm sure this child will be welcomed by the master.
我肯定主人会欢迎这个孩子的到来
He was longing for a child, after all.
毕竟 他一直很想要个孩子
As long as I'm on this farm,
只要我待在他农场的一天
I will be able to peacefully
我就能好好地
raise a healthy child.
带大一个健康的孩子
So, Einar...
所以 埃纳尔
Let things be
就这样吧
until the storm passes.
等着风暴过去吧
Let things be...
就这样吧...
I thought you were
我以为你会...
going to wait for the storm to pass,
等待着风暴过去
Arnheid.
阿奴纳
You were listening, Old Master?
你都听到了吗 老主人?
You guys seem to think I've gone completely senile,
你们全都以为我老人痴呆了
but my mind is still working fine. Don't underestimate me.
但我的神智仍然很清醒 别小看我了
I just want to care for his wounds, that's all.
我只是想照料他的伤口而已
I know
我知道
that I shouldn't see him anymore.
我不该再见他
And yet, I don't know why...
但是 我不知道为什么...
There was a time
有段时间
when I also waited patiently for a storm to pass.
我也曾想要耐心等待着风暴过去
Actually, I was just hiding.
实际上 我只是东躲西藏
While trembling...
一直在担惊受怕
This was more than 20 years ago.
这是20多年前的事了
At the time, my son Ketil
那个时候 我的儿子凯特尔
and a beautiful girl from the same town had fallen in love with each other.
和同村的一个美丽女孩陷入爱河
But one day,
但有一天
that girl caught the eye of Ebbe, a man who was
艾比注意到了那位美丽的女孩
gradually increasing his influence in the surrounding area.
艾比当时正在附近区域 逐渐扩大自己的势力
We were forced to make a difficult decision.
我们被逼得做出了一个痛苦的决定
Ketil was ready to take up arms
凯特尔为了保护那个女孩
in order to protect the girl.
已经卷起袖子准备大干一场了
But at the time, we weren't as powerful as we are now
但那个时候 我们的力量不如现在这么强大
and many feared Ebbe.
很多人都很害怕艾比
They thought we would be destroyed if we went against his wishes.
他们认为如果我们不按照他说的去做 我们的下场就会很凄惨
In the end, we decided
最后 我们的决定是
to obey.
顺从他
How can I call myself a Nordic man...?
我怎么能够称自己是北方人?
I offered up a girl
我为了救自己一命
just to save my own skin.
拱手献上了一名女子
Then...
然后
on the girl's wedding day...
在女孩婚礼的那天
It was the act of
有个厌恶艾比且觊觎他财富的人
a man who loathed Ebbe and envied his wealth.
发动了攻击
By the time we heard the news and rushed over there,
等到我们听到消息赶过去的时候
everything had been burned down already.
一切早已被烧毁
Why...?
为什么?
Why do these things always happen?
为什么这种事要一再上演?
All I can say is that...
我只是想说...
you may be able to let the storm pass
你或许能够等待风暴过去
but it will still leave you with scars.
但你仍然会因此留下伤疤
I'm sorry I can't be of any help.
很抱歉 我帮不上什么忙
I will be right back.
我很快就会回来
"Storm."
风暴
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻译:朱未耒